<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"> <channel><title>Sammons Lab Research - Blog</title> <description>Science updates on transcription factors, chromatin, and p53 biology from the Sammons Lab at the State University of New York at Albany</description><link></link> <atom:link href="/feed.category.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/> <item><title>Does Excel excel?</title> <description>&lt;p&gt;I need to admit this right off the bat: I still use Microsoft Excel to do a significant portion of my data analysis. My trainees do as well. And deep down, I do not think there is nearly the problem with using Excel (or other spreadsheet software alternatives like LibreOffice) that many in the computer science/bioinformatics world might lead you to believe. There is something to be said for simplicity and for being able to actually &amp;quot;see&amp;quot; and interact with your data. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would be (more) of a fool if I didn&amp;#39;t say there are extreme limitations to Excel that preclude its use on large datasets. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These include 1. row &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; column limits&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;severe trouble with sorting lists by any feature other than by numerical values,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;problems with reproducible workflows, scripting, and data formats, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;most importantly&lt;/strong&gt;, automatic formatting that leads to data analysis errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;These items are summarized incredibly well in a recent &lt;a href="https://peerj.com/preprints/3183/"&gt;PeerJ Preprint&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think this is an essential read for anyone who uses spreadsheets to collect data (so, most of us!) &lt;/p&gt; </description> <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate><link>/blog/spreadsheets/</link> <guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/spreadsheets/</guid> </item> </channel> </rss>